准备好了吗  孩子们
Are you ready, kids?
好了船长
Aye aye, captain
我听不见
I can't hear you
好了船长
Aye aye, captain
是谁住在深海的大菠萝里
Who lives in a pineapple under the sea?
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
方方黄黄伸缩自如
Absorbent and yellow and porous is he
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
如果四处探险是你的愿望
If nautical nonsense be something you wish
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
那就敲敲甲板让大鱼开路
Then drop on the deck and flop like a fish
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
准备
Ready
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
黑猩猩驾到
分镜总监
编剧
翻译: 1440kHz
技术总监
动画总监
制片指导
本字幕仅限学习交流
严禁用于商业用途
邮件
来了
It's here
看好了  派大星
Behold, Patrick
官方正品高菲高伯挠背器
The official Goofy Goober back scratcher
才用了52个盒盖换来的
And it only cost me 52 box tops
好耶  爽啊
Oh, yeah, that's it
我试试看
Let me try
派大星
Patrick
那不是挠背器
that's not the back scratcher
是我胳膊
That's my arm
抱歉
Sorry
这种好东西可不能我们独享
You know, we shouldn't keep this all to ourselves
应该让章鱼哥来试试看
We should let Squidward try it out
好
Yeah
出发
Onward
去章鱼哥家
to Squidward's house
滚开
Go away
去珊迪家
To Sandy's house
珊迪  你得看看这个
Hey, Sandy, you gotta see this
珊迪
Sandy?
怎么回事
What's going on here?
珊迪  没事吧
Sandy, are you okay?
怎么了  珊迪
What's wrong, Sandy?
他们来了
They're coming
黑猩猩要来了
The chimps are coming
谁啊
Who?
我老板
My bosses
要过来视察了
They're coming for an inspection
我连着一周都在没日没夜地工作
I've worked day and night for a week
结果我每样发明都好不到哪去
but none of my inventions are any good
要是今天下午前还造不出伟大的发明
If I don't have a real impressive invention
by this afternoon
我经费就要被砍了
they'll cut my funding
只能离开裤头村了
and I'll have to leave Bikini Bottom
没事  珊迪
Come on, Sandy
你肯定发明过不少有用的东西
I'll bet you invented lots of useful things
这个头盔看着就挺伟大
This helmet looks impressive
能干什么用
What's it do?
戴了就能跟坚果对话
It lets you talk to nuts
又有什么用
What use is that?
海绵宝宝呼叫花生
SpongeBob to Peanut
请回答  花生
Come in, Peanut
它说什么
What's it saying?
它说
It says
里面好黑啊
"It's dark in here"
还有别的发明吗  珊迪
Got anything else, Sandy?
这是我的坚果咖啡机
There's my nuttachino machine
能用任何坚果做出泡沫多的热咖啡
It makes a nice hot, frothy cup of any nut you choose
最后是我的全自动胡桃夹子机
And lastly, my fully automated nutcracker
胡桃
我连个简单的胡桃夹子都做不好
I can't even make a simple nutcracker
就只是有点小毛病嘛
So, it's got a few bugs
我跟派大星可以帮你修好的
Patrick and I'll help you fix it
对吧  派大星
Right, Patrick?
派大星
Patrick?
不会有事的
Everything'll be fine
没用的  海绵宝宝
It's no use, SpongeBob
我只好面对现实了
I just have to face facts
我要离开裤头村  因为
I'll be leaving Bikini Bottom because
我是个废物
I'm a failure
不能让珊迪就这么离开  派大星
We can't let Sandy leave, Patrick
要怎么办
What'll we do?
她老板要找发明  对吧
They're looking for an invention, right?
对
Right
那咱就开始发明吧
So let's start inventing
好耶
Yeah
该认真起来了  派大星
It's time to get serious, Patrick
对
Right
我有新发明了
I made an invention
是根可以拿来写字跟画画的棍子
It's a stick that you can draw or write stuff with
那叫铅笔  派大星
That's a pencil, Patrick
早就发明了
It's already been invented
这个发明好
This is a good one
是个可以发光的玻璃球
It's a glass ball that lights up
这样就可以在黑暗里看见东西了
so you can see in the dark
灯泡  早就发明了
Light bulb, already invented
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob
这个发明肯定行
I know this one will work
我发明了个平行宇宙
I've invented a parallel universe
那叫镜子  派大星
That's a mirror, Patrick
早就发明了
It's already been invented
有人老是盗我创意
Somebody keeps stealing my ideas
我觉得你那创意挺不错的
Well, I thought it was a pretty good idea
我放弃
I give up
我什么都发明不出来
I'll never invent anything
公交
再见  裤头村
So long, Bikini Bottom
我无法不辞而别
I can't leave without a good-bye
但千万别看不起我
But please don't think bad of me
假如我开始哭泣
If'n I start to cry
再见  裤头村
So long, Bikini Bottom
有不少事物我都很想念
There's so many things I'll miss
从你拥挤的雾都
From your smoggy, crowded city
再到蜇人的水母
To your stingin' jellyfish
这里充满着不少事物
This town is filled with many things
我样样都很爱
That I've come to love
从地上飞行的鸟儿
From the birds that fly upon the ground
再到空中的花儿
To the flowers up above
再见  裤头村
Farewell, Bikini Bottom
我一点也不愿离开
Now, I really hate to go
因为这一切当中我最想念的
'Cause the things I'll miss the most of all
就是我认识的好朋友们
Are the friends I've come to know
我真为自己感到羞愧  派大星
I'm ashamed of myself, Patrick
我这么快就放弃了
I gave up too quickly
一定要给珊迪的老板造出神发明
We'll build Sandy's bosses an invention so amazing
让他们一辈子都非给珊迪经费不可
they'll give Sandy funding forever
汽水
完成了  派大星
We've done it, Patrick
我们造出了全世界史上最伟大的发明
We created the greatest invention
the world has ever seen
派大星  他们来了
Patrick, they're here
谁啊
Who?
珊迪的老板
Sandy's bosses
就因为他们  我们才忙活一下午发明
The reason we spent all afternoon inventing
我不知道你在说什么
I have no idea what you're talking about
你们好  先生们
Good day, gentlemen
我来给大家介绍一下
Allow me to introduce ourselves
我是珀西教授
I am Professor Percy
这位是果酱博士
This is Dr. Marmalade
听候差遣
At your service
这位是雷金纳德巨头
And this is Lord Reginald
幸会
Charmed
你们几个讲话真好笑
You guys talk funny
多说一点
Say more words
我们是树屋企业有限公司董事会
We are the board of directors
of Tree Dome Enterprises Limited
前来视察
and we are here to ascertain
奇克斯小姐的发明是否达标
if Miss Cheek's inventions are up to snuff
珊迪的科学知识造福了这里所有居民
Why, everyone in town has benefited
from Sandy's scientific knowledge
珊迪出现以前  我瘦不拉几
Before Sandy showed up, I used to be a scrawny weakling
我那时候很傻
And I used to be dumb
的确
Quite
请问您尊姓大名
And whom do I have the pleasure of addressing?
我叫海绵宝宝
My name is SpongeBob
我是派大星教授
And I am Professor Patrick
什么教授
Professor?
派大星博士加教授
Doctor Professor Patrick
别理他
Don't mind him
实习生是这样的
You know how interns are
奇克斯小姐呢
Where is Miss Cheeks?
她随时都会回来
She should be back any moment
我还以为她跑路了
I thought she ran away
就因为她什么都不会发明
because she couldn't invent anything
派大星
Patrick
叫我派大星博士加教授先生
That's Mr. Doctor Professor Patrick to you
你不觉得现在得展示珊迪的发明了吗
Don't you think it's time to show them Sandy's invention
派大星博士加教授先生
Mr. Doctor Professor Patrick?
好啊
Good idea
干嘛
Well?
你是免费上班的实习生
You're the unpaid intern
你来干活
You do the work
先生们  我可以毫不夸张地说
Gentlemen, I can say without exaggeration
这就是全宇宙史上最重要的发明
that this is the most important invention
in the history of the universe
为你们献上
I give you
全自动挠背机
the Automatic Back Scratcher
加梳头机加挖鼻机
Hair Comber, Nose Picker
加尤克里里调音机9000
and Ukulele Tuner 9000
派大星博士加教授
最强
我们的科研经费全花在这玩意上了吗
This is where our research money went?
很棒吧
Isn't it great?
一个全自动挠背机加梳头机
An automatic back-scratcher, hair-combing
加挖鼻机加尤克里里调音机
nose-picking ukulele tuner
好好好  那话我早听过了
Yes, well, I've heard that claim before
行
Yes
敢问这个装置是怎么运行的
How do we know this contraption works?
来演示一下
Let's see a demonstration
请上前一步
Step right up
你好像不是很注重个人卫生啊
You look like you've been neglecting
your personal hygiene
我吗
Me?
你确定这样安全吗
Are you sure this is safe?
跟我是博士加教授一样确定
As sure as I'm a doctor professor
派大星  你不觉得该测试一下吗
Patrick, don't you think we should test it?
好啊
Okay
跟我想的不太一样
That's not exactly what I had in mind
雷金纳德巨头  你没事吧
Lord Reginald, are you all right?
天啊
I say
太厉害了
This is splendid
实在是厉害
Absolutely splendid
这是什么
What's this?
不可思议
Marvelous
这机器把我鼻孔里的残渣清理干净了
This machine has evacuated my nostrils
of unwanted residue
而且还很舒服
in a manner most pleasant
干得漂亮  派大星博士加教授先生
Good work, Mr. Doctor Professor Patrick
谢谢  低级助理
Thank you, lowly assistant
现在它在喂我美味的布丁
I say, now it's feeding me delicious pudding
布丁  我不记得发明里面有布丁来着
Pudding, I don't remember that part of the invention
机器在给我尤克里里调音了
And now it's tuning my ukulele
有那个必要吗
I say, was that necessary?
先生  你太无礼了
You, sir, are impertinent
天啊
Oh, dear
雷金纳德巨头  你没事吧
Lord Reginald, are you all right?
抱歉  你那意思是没事吗
I'm sorry, was that a yes?
派大星博士加教授先生
Mr. Doctor Professor Patrick
这是什么意思
what is the meaning of this?
没事的
It's okay
那声惨烈的尖叫
The horrible screaming
表示机器运转很顺利
means that it's working
真希望珊迪还在这里
I really wish Sandy were here
上车了
All aboard
无处可去时  这趟车还会带你远走吗
Will this bus take you somewhere
when you've got nowhere else to go?
会啊
It sure does
这趟车会停逃兵村
We make stops in Quittersville
孬种镇跟废物堡
Failuretown and Loserburg
怎么回事
What in tarnation?
这是在耍什么猴戏
What's with all the monkey business?
珊迪
Sandy
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob
这到底是怎么回事
What the heck is going on here?
成功了
It works
雷金纳德巨头  你没事吧
Lord Reginald, are you all right?
我的傲慢似乎被打破了
I seem to have ruptured my pomposity
我们应该关闭这间树屋
We shall commence closure of this establishment
立刻执行
immediately
说实话  我都开始怀疑
Frankly, I'm beginning to question
这海底树屋到底有没有经济效益了
the economic benefits of underwater tree domes
说到底也没多大意义
Doesn't make much sense when you get right down to it
对不起  珊迪
I'm sorry, Sandy
我们想把你留在裤头村
We were trying to keep you in Bikini Bottom
可我们的所作所为害你没机会再留了
but all we did was ruin your chances to stay
反正我本来也快被开除了
I was about to be fired anyway
谢谢你尽力帮忙  海绵宝宝
Thanks for trying to help, SpongeBob
也谢谢你  派大星
You, too, Patrick
叫我派大星博士加教授先生
That's Mr. Doctor Professor Patrick
别得寸进尺
Don't push it
抱歉
Sorry
我们要走了  果酱博士
We are departing, Dr. Marmalade
天啊
My word
激动了老半天
All of this excitement
搞得我体内的钾含量都降低了
has drastically reduced my potassium levels
好家伙
Good gracious
该不会是
Can it be?
再来一次
Try it again
是真的
It is
是我们找了117年的剥香蕉机
It's the banana peeler
we have been searching 117 years for
珊迪  他们为你的胡桃夹子发狂了
Sandy, they're going bananas for your nutcracker
香 蕉
确实
Yeah
奇克斯小姐
Well, Miss Cheeks
不得不说
I must say
你已经大大超出了我们的期望
you have exceeded expectations
虽然可能我脑袋受重伤  糊涂了
It may be the extreme head trauma I've suffered
但我要给你签订一份为期20年的合同
but I am going to offer you a 20-year contract
而且要涨不少经费
with a substantial pay rise
我接受
I accept
万岁
Hooray
我期望你造出伟大发明  奇克斯小姐
I expect great things out of you, Miss Cheeks
伟大的发明
Great things
也许你可以把你的才华
Perhaps you could put your talents
全身心投入全自动投屎机的制造
toward that automatic poop-throwing machine
我们很长时间都没搞懂那玩意
that's eluded us for so long
好了好了
Now, now
奇迹得一个一个来
One miracle at a time
再见
Good-bye
现在就只差想办法解决一下
Well, the only thing left is to figure out what to do
这个麻烦的装置了
with this infernal contraption
到我了
My turn
好耶
All right
老鬼当家
分镜总监
翻译: 1440kHz
编剧
技术总监
动画总监
制片指导
本字幕仅限学习交流
严禁用于商业用途
裤头村
这个该死的幽雾真是可恶
Curse this cursed, ghostly fog
我连自己鼻子都快看不清了
I can barely see past me own nose
我的船
Me ship
喂  道路救援吗
Hello, roadside assistance?
我这边爆胎了
I've got a bit of a flat
我要在什么地方等待救援
My location where I'll be staying?
商业区还是居民区
Business or residence?
居民区
Residence
是飞天魔鬼
The Flying Dutchman
你来我家干什么
What are you doing in my house?
我船送去修了  只好困在这里
I'm stuck here while me ship is being repaired
修好之前  我要缠上你
Till then, I'm here to haunt ya
章鱼哥
Squidward
章鱼哥  救命
Squidward, help
章鱼哥  一定要救救我啊
Squidward, you have to help me
我家里有有有  有鬼啊
There's a gh-gh-gh, a ghost in my house
海绵宝宝  我得跟你说多少次
SpongeBob, how many times do I have to tell you
我不相信有鬼  而且我不喜欢你
I don't believe in ghosts, and I never liked you?
派大星
Patrick
派大星  你得救救我
Patrick, you've got to help me
是飞天魔
The Flying Dutch
鬼
man
小蜗
Gary
休想伤害我的小蜗
Don't you dare hurt my little Gary
我只是想摸摸这个小家伙而已
I just wanted to pet the little guy
没事了  飞天魔鬼不会伤害你的
There, there, Dutchie's not gonna hurt you
我就喜欢来只上好的蜗牛
I love me a good snail
小蜗
Gary
放开来吓一吓最爽了
Nothing better than giving a good scare
没事了  小蜗
It's okay, Gary
可别太舒服了
Don't get too comfortable
晚安  小蜗
Good night, Gary
海草哥麦片
飞天魔鬼  你该不会还要再闹吧
Dutchie, is this gonna be much longer?
你怎么不怕啊  小子
Why aren't you freaking out, lad?
你都已经住一阵子了
Well, you've been here a while
我呢
and, uh
早看完你所有花招了
I've seen all your tricks
你想表达什么
What are you trying to say?
我知道自己大势将去
I know when I'm washed up
我多年以来就只会那老一套
I've been doing the same material for years
只有年轻小伙才吓得动别人
Scaring is a young man's game
是时候该放弃了
It's time to give up the ghost
不是真不当鬼了
No pun intended
不对不对
Oh, no, no
我只是说我习惯了  就这样
I meant that I'm just used to it, that's all
别骗我
Don't lie to me
你只是得去吓吓别人而已
You've just got to scare someone other than me
优惠床垫
介意我试试看吗
Mind if I test it out?
好啊  躺得好舒服
Yeah, this does feel comfortable
能先失陪一下吗
Could you excuse me a moment?
算了吧
Forget it
你觉得怎么样
So, what do you think?
正式确认了
It's official
我再也不可怕了
I'm not scary anymore
你说的都是什么鬼话
Just what kind of talk is that?
你就只是状态没以前好了  仅此而已
You're just off your game, that's all
也许我得休息一下
Maybe I just need a break
就是  稍微放个假
Take some time off, you know?
好啊  放松一下
Sure, relax a little
也许还得找个朋友住一阵子
Maybe stay with a friend for a while
住在菠萝屋里  躺在舒服的沙发上
On a comfy couch in a pineapple
再住得久那么一点点
Just for a little while longer?
住到我恢复如初
Till I get back on me feet?
六个月后
第一名  你还
Hey, champ, how's it
大声点
Turn it up
调大声一点
Turn the knob up
谁能想到我们竟然有这么多共同点啊
Who'd guess we have so much in common?
你喜欢泰迪熊
You like teddy bears
我喜欢泰迪熊
I like teddy bears
你喜欢小马
You like ponies
我喜欢小马
I like ponies
那是婚戒吗
Is that a wedding ring?
这个啊
This?
没什么
It's nothing
这到底是怎么一回事
What is going on around here?
海绵宝宝  别那么扫兴嘛
Come on, SpongeBob, don't be a stick in the mud
下面的小心了
Look out below
怎么样
How was that?
第三次还更棒了
Even better the third time
不行
Oh, no
绝对绝对不行
No, no, no, no, no
全都给我出去
Everyone, get out
行了  派对已经结束了
All righty, boys, party's over
该走了  亲爱的
Time to scoot honey
飞天魔鬼  你是想一辈子瘫沙发上吗
Dutchie, do you want to spend eternity on this couch?
沙发可舒服了
Well, it is comfy
照照镜子
Look in the mirror
你都已经魂不附体了
You're a ghost of your former self
你说得对  海绵宝宝
You're right, SpongeBob
我好可悲
I'm pathetic
确实如此
Yes, you are
但咱要帮你摆脱你那龌龊的处境
But we're going to raise you up
from your squalid condition
用可视化的材料指引你
through the use of visual aids
看好了
Watch now
这到底是什么破玩意
What in barnacles is it?
自我觉醒之旅
A journey into self-awareness
内在的力量
The power within
好
Yeah
真是太美了
That was beautiful
快从沙发上站起来
Now get off of that couch
穿好衣服  飞天魔鬼
and into your clothes, Dutchman
该要认真起来了
It's time to get serious
先从简单的开始
Let's start you off easy
你觉得自己能吓倒那个老太婆吗
You think you can take that old lady down there?
你开什么玩笑
What, are you kidding me?
吓她可太简单了
Scaring her is too easy
这才是我认识的飞天魔鬼嘛
Now that's the Flying Dutchman I know
这就去把空谈化为行动
Let's see you put those words into action
没问题  朋友
No problemo, compadre
朗尼  是你吗
Lonnie, is that you?
什么
What?
不对
No
是我  不祥的飞天魔鬼
'Tis I, the ominous Flying Dutchman
朗尼  有种好用的新产品叫做牙膏
Lonnie, there's this great new product
called toothpaste
你应该用用看
I think you should try it
健身房
开始吧
Let's hit it
兄弟  看看你的胸肌
Dude, look at your pecs
你可真了不起
You're phenomenal
身子可真硬朗
Truly a hard body
看看这二头肌
Look at those guns
吓到他了
Now he's got him
我的背阔肌有些松弛了
My latissimus dorsi has gone flabby
得上划船练习架了
I've got to get to a rowing machine
没用的  海绵宝宝
It's no use, SpongeBob
我好像就是吓不到人
I can't seem to scare anyone
可能大家都再也不相信鬼了
Maybe people just don't believe in ghosts anymore
等一下
Wait a minute
你刚给了我解决你所有问题的答案
I think you just gave me the answer to all your problems
妖精
goblins
愧疚感
guilt trip
章鱼哥
Squidward
怎么了
What's going on?
你怎么不给我打电话
Why haven't you called me?
妈
Mother?
你干嘛不给你妈打电话
Why haven't you called your mother?
章鱼哥很爱妈妈
Squiddums loves his mama
那你干嘛不给我打电话
Why don't you call me then?
干嘛不给我打电话
Why don't you call me?
听说你不相信鬼
I heard you don't believe in ghosts
鬼吗
Ghosts?
我就是飞天魔鬼
As in the Flying Dutchman
世上根本没有鬼
There's no such thing as ghosts
没有鬼
No such things
根本没有鬼吗
No such thing as ghosts?
你不相信有鬼吗
You don't believe in ghosts?
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob?
可怕
Scary
不要
No
根本不可能
That's impossible
鬼啊
Ghosts
飞天魔鬼  成功了
Dutchie, it worked
你又可怕起来了
You got your scare back
而且也自信回来了
And me confidence, too
感觉我可以狠狠吓别人一跳了
Now I feel like I could
scare the living criminy out of anybody
全都多亏了有你  我的小子
All thanks to you, my boy
也许你的船马上就可以修好了
And maybe your ship will be repaired soon
其实我有话要坦白  海绵宝宝
Actually, I have a confession, SpongeBob
我的船三个月前就修好了
My ship's been done for three months now
能跟你当室友可真高兴
Well, it was nice rooming with ya
对了  差点忘了
Oh, yeah, I almost forgot
我给你留了点小小的补偿
I left you a little something something
for all your trouble
现在我要去摧毁更多灵魂了
Now it's high time for me to ruin more souls
好个飞天魔鬼
Good ol' Dutchie